<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Diotrephes detected, corrected, and rejected, and Archippus admonished: by a soft answer to an angry sermon and book lately published, intituled, A true account of what was done, at the casting of two members out of Mr. Stucleys congregation in Exon</title>
            <author>E. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64197</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830664</idno>
  <idno type="VID">35117</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240875246</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing T4E</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219145</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830664</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99830664e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64197)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35117)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2080:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Diotrephes detected, corrected, and rejected, and Archippus admonished: by a soft answer to an angry sermon and book lately published, intituled, A true account of what was done, at the casting of two members out of Mr. Stucleys congregation in Exon</title>
                  <author>E. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M.S. for Henry Cripps and are to be sold at his shop in Popes Head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 18: E.T.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Mall, Thomas. A true account of what was done by a Church of Christ in Exon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Mall, Thomas, b. 1629 or 30. --  True account of what was done by a Church of Christ in Exon --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Excommunication --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35117:1"/>
            <p>DIOTREPHES Detected, Corrected, and Rejected, AND ARCHIPPUS ADMONISHED BY A soft Answer to an Angry Sermon and <hi>Book</hi> lately Published, Intituled, <hi>A True Account of what was done,</hi> at the casting of two Members out of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Stucleys</hi> Congregation in <hi>Exon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> Job <hi>answered</hi> (Zophar, Eliphaz, <hi>and</hi> Bildad <hi>his</hi> Teachers, <hi>and</hi> Reprovers, <hi>who</hi> so Reprochfully <hi>accused him of</hi> Lying, Mocking, <hi>&amp;c.) and said: O-that mine</hi> Adversary <hi>had written</hi> a Booke, <hi>I would take it upon my shoulder, and binde it as</hi> a Crowne <hi>to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>(Job <hi>chap. 11, 12, &amp;</hi> 31. with 16. 10 <hi>&amp;</hi> 19. 3.)</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou-hast made me wiser then mine</hi> Enemies,-<hi>I have more understanding then all my</hi> Teachers.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>(Psalm</hi> 119. 98, 99.)</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>For a Bishop <hi>must be blamelesse,</hi> of <hi>good behaviour,</hi> no <hi>striker,</hi> but <hi>Patient,</hi> or <hi>Gentle,</hi> not <hi>Angry,</hi> not <hi>Froward,</hi> not <hi>self-willed,</hi> not <hi>a Brawler,</hi> not <hi>a Novice,</hi> lest being lifted up with <hi>Pride,</hi> he fall into the condemnation of the Devil:</p>
               <bibl>(1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. &amp; <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 7.)</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>But <hi>Diotrephes</hi> (who <hi>loveth</hi> to have the <hi>preheminence)—Prateth</hi> against us with <hi>Malicious words,</hi>—and <hi>casteth</hi> the Brethren <hi>out of the Church:</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>(Job. Epist. 3. v 9, 10.)</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now we</hi> command <hi>you, Brethren, in the Name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye</hi> withdraw your selves from every Brother <hi>that walketh</hi> Disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, <hi>and not after the Tradition which he received of us: And if</hi> any man obey not our word, &amp;c. Note <hi>that man, and</hi> have no company with him, <hi>that he may be ashamed: yet</hi> count <hi>him not as</hi> an enemy, <hi>but</hi> admonish him as a Brother.</p>
               <bibl>(2 Thess. 3. 6. 14, 15)</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Henry Cripps</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop in <hi>Popes Head</hi> Alley, 1658.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:35117:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35117:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Brother Stucley,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SO I call you, though <hi>walking disorderly,</hi> and <hi>not obeying the Word of Christ and his Apostles in their Epistles and Rules for Church-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings:</hi> In which respect though I <hi>cannot Joyn or company with you</hi> in <hi>Church communion,</hi> nor <hi>praise</hi> your <hi>Church proceeding,</hi> that you may be a little <hi>ashamed</hi> of your <hi>late-doings,</hi> yet how ever I shall not <hi>Account you as an enemy,</hi> but shall rather endeavour to <hi>Admonish you as a brother, as I am directed in</hi> 2 Thess. 3. 14, 15. And our Saviour Christ I finde (whose example indeed we should strive to immitate) was so <hi>Gentle</hi> and <hi>meeke</hi> in his <hi>Appellation of some</hi> of the worst of sinners as that he calleth him <hi>Friend</hi> who had not on the <hi>Wedding Garment:</hi> Therefore I affect not any way of <hi>Retort,</hi> as to say (in your <hi>own dialect) wretched man, proud-man, lawles-man, lying man, perjured man, covenant breaker, Child of hell, Notorious Lyer, Di<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>contented Lyer, Bryer in our sides, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion fitter for damned Spirits, &amp;c.</hi> nor to say (in the <hi>like manner of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression) Blinde Guide, False-Teacher, Church Robber, Over-Ruler, Lorder over Gods Heritage, Ʋsurper of the Churches Power and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp;c.</hi> upon Pretence <hi>(according to the argument in your late Book, Page</hi> 11<seg rend="sup">th</seg>) that you may be so <hi>VISIBLY,</hi> (or <hi>appeare</hi> in Print so) though you are not so <hi>Invisibly,</hi> or in <hi>Reallity.</hi> This truly were but the <hi>Rendring of evill for evill, and Railing for Railing,</hi> or <hi>Reviling for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling,</hi> and these <hi>Revilers,</hi> I find also <hi>WITH-OƲT,</hi> even amongst as <hi>infamous Associates</hi> as the <hi>Lyers.</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9, 10) Me thinks (Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>soft words</hi> and <hi>hard arguments</hi> were much better: Indeed <hi>He that appeareth first in his own cause seemeth Just</hi> (as Solomon speakes) <hi>but his neighbour cometh after and sifteth him:</hi> So if I may but <hi>Come after</hi> you a little, and <hi>observe</hi> some of the most <hi>materiall things</hi> in my <hi>way,</hi> I may possibly tell you (though you are your selfe <hi>a Teacher</hi> and <hi>guide of others)</hi> yet <hi>here</hi> you are in <hi>an Errour, and this is not your way: J<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b</hi> would not <hi>Dispise</hi> the <hi>Cause</hi> of his <hi>Man servant,</hi> nor of his <hi>Maid servant</hi> when they <hi>Contended</hi> with him: And though <hi>Naaman</hi> at first <hi>Dispised</hi> the <hi>Advice</hi> of the Prophet when his <hi>Passion</hi> was up, yet after when he was in a better frame, He could <hi>Hearken</hi> also to the <hi>Advice</hi> of his <hi>Servants</hi> whilst they <hi>Argued</hi> and <hi>Reasoned</hi> with him; And so did <hi>David to the Advice of</hi> Abigail, <hi>when she mett him in the way,</hi> And if <hi>you can doe the like to mine,</hi> (whilest I am now <hi>contending</hi> with you this day,) the Lord may peradventure (even by <hi>so weake an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument) shew you yet a more excellent way;</hi> Surely, <hi>The wrath of man
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35117:3"/> will not accomplish the Righteousnesse of God,</hi> and Passion in the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, will but stirre up passion in the Reproved, and what good (thinke you) will it doe, to Reprove pride in others, with a manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of far greater pride in our selves? How unlike is this to our Lord and Master? whose <hi>voyce</hi> (you know) <hi>was not heard in the streets:</hi> and who hath commanded you as you are <hi>his Servant</hi> and the <hi>Churches Servant</hi> also, to be <hi>Gentle</hi> towards <hi>all Men,</hi> and <hi>Patient,</hi> and <hi>Long-suffering,</hi> and <hi>to wait</hi> if <hi>so be God at any time would give them Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the acknowledgment of the tru<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h,</hi> that you think <hi>doe oppose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves thereunto,</hi> What? Can you not <hi>Reprove,</hi> and <hi>cast out</hi> (of <hi>your Church,</hi> I think I may call it,) but you must do it angrily, and vexingly, and frettingly, and ridgedly, and vauntingly, and selfe-honouringly, (as if none of your Neighbours were such a strict <hi>Disciplinarian</hi> as you) and also enviously? What do you Grieve and Repine and Envy at it, because some <hi>Reall Invisible-Saints</hi> (though for want of some Eye-Salve your sight at present is not good enough to see them <hi>Visible-Ones)</hi> are in <hi>Esteeme</hi> amongst the <hi>Godly</hi> where they live, and are by them <hi>Countenanced</hi> (though by <hi>you</hi> and <hi>your major part of the Brethren Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated,)</hi> and that they are of <hi>Good Report also amongst those that are without,</hi> yea, <hi>that their praise also is in all the Churches</hi> where they have been heard of or spoken off, and that <hi>the Godly</hi> though of <hi>other Judgements</hi> (in some things) yet doe <hi>Honour them so as to give them the Chiefe seats in their Publick meeting places</hi> (as Page 22) and so in these things have <hi>Countenance indeed</hi> and <hi>an Interest indeed</hi> (as you say Page 15<seg rend="sup">th</seg> &amp; 90<seg rend="sup">th</seg>) and that both in the Heart of <hi>God</hi> and of <hi>Men,</hi> being herein like their Saviour, <hi>who</hi> (you know) <hi>Increased in Wisdome and in Stature, and in favour with God and men:</hi> and also like those primitive Saints <hi>(Acts</hi> 2. last.) <hi>who</hi> (whatever they suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered) still Rejoyced, (and so it seemes doe these, at which you are troubled) <hi>Praising God, and having Favour with all the People:</hi> Whilest you (alasle) are <hi>Slighted,</hi> and <hi>Disesteemed</hi> and <hi>Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalued,</hi> and <hi>Annihilated,</hi> notwithstanding that you doe <hi>Magnifie your office,</hi> and bestirre your selfe so exceedingly, (a little more indeed then become, you) and have put your selfe to so great <hi>expence</hi> and <hi>charge</hi> (notwithstanding your condemning of women for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of <hi>Expensive</hi> company and meetings) for these <hi>Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred Books,</hi> which (if Reports are True) your Bookseller hath sent you (I suppose,) to <hi>disperse,</hi> for the <hi>excusing</hi> of this your <hi>Miscarriage,</hi> or for the yet honouring of you before the people: You not minding it (it seemes) that <hi>your selfe</hi> and <hi>fellow-officers</hi> are to be dealt with as well <hi>as private Members,</hi> and to be <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35117:3"/> Cast out, Rejected</hi> and <hi>withdrawn from,</hi> when you speak and Act in your <hi>own spirits,</hi> your <hi>own voyce,</hi> your <hi>own wills,</hi> your <hi>own wrath,</hi> your <hi>own passions,</hi> and <hi>proceed</hi> and <hi>Transact things</hi> in the house of God <hi>obstinately</hi> or <hi>wilfully</hi> after <hi>Dissatifaction declared,</hi> contrary to Christs <hi>Appointment</hi> and <hi>Institution,</hi> Namely without the <hi>Full</hi> and <hi>Free consent, Concurrence</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of the <hi>whole Church,</hi> as your Book it selfe Expresses apparently, which tells us <hi>The Officers and Major part of the Brethren</hi> must doe these things, and <hi>that they are the Church:</hi> But if they are the Church Surely they are such a Church as is not to be found in the Old or New Testament; but in Civill or Worldly Corporations indeed you have such a Church or Civill-Assembly as doe Transact and carry things by Majority of voyces: And if it be come to <hi>this</hi> even in our <hi>Congregationall Churches;</hi> Then surely many of the <hi>private Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of these Churches, (and such it may be as by the <hi>Officers</hi> are <hi>least esteemed in the Church)</hi> may yet in an holy Humility, begin to praise the Lord with the Psalmist <hi>(Psalm 119.) That he hath been pleased through his Commandements to make them wiser then their Enemies and to give them more understanding</hi> (in the affairs of Christs house) <hi>then all their Teachers,</hi> yea then their <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Leaders,</hi> who (if they should follow them) <hi>would cause them to erre</hi> (as Isa. 9 16.) And though you may thinke your selfe to be <hi>an Apollo,</hi> and <hi>mighty in the Scriptures,</hi> as wel as in your <hi>Numerous Quotation of the Fathers,</hi> (That would have men <hi>Excommunicated</hi> for 3 times absence from their Assemblies, if they can but procure the <hi>Major part of the Brethren</hi> to joyne with some <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trephes</hi> in the worke, yet (why may not some <hi>Priscilla</hi> take you to taske <hi>and shew you the way of God yet more perfectly?</hi> and tell you (as Christ speaks to some others in a like case) <hi>that from the Beginning it was not so:</hi> It was not so as you and your <hi>Omnium-Gatherum</hi> of <hi>Church-Fathers &amp; Docters</hi> have <hi>Said &amp; Acted.</hi> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you have failed not only in <hi>Manner</hi> (as you expresly confesse Page the last:) but also in <hi>Matter:</hi> it may be worth the while to fall close to the Businesse, and (if the Lord will) to hold forth something that may convince you thereof: that so you may be Gained, which is my Soules desire and prayer to God for you: that the Name of Christ may not further suffer by the like <hi>unadvisednesse</hi> and <hi>Rashnesse</hi> in <hi>others:</hi> Which (should they Imitate you in) would be the most likely Means upon Earth to <hi>Breake</hi> and <hi>Scatter all the Churches of Christ in these Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> more then ever that <hi>Persecution</hi> from the Powers of the World which <hi>arose about Stephen</hi> did that <hi>Primitive Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, then: If <hi>the same Power must cast out, that receives in:</hi> (when occasion is for it) Then the <hi>Private Members</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> who cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35117:4"/>
               <hi>you</hi> and your <hi>brethren</hi> into <hi>office</hi> must again <hi>Out you</hi> when such occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion shall be, though they have not an <hi>Officer</hi> unbiassed and uncorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted left amongst you to lead the Action of this Excommunication The Rule you know is, <hi>Say to Archippus, Take heed to thy Ministery,</hi> (Coloss. 4. 17.) <hi>That is,</hi> Take heed not only what thou <hi>say'st,</hi> but what thou <hi>dost in the House of God,</hi> and <hi>How thou dost</hi> every thing also? Namely, that it be <hi>according to Rule,</hi> and the <hi>Pattern</hi> in the <hi>Primitive Churches;</hi> and <hi>so,</hi> and no otherwise, but as the true <hi>Annoynting</hi> which they also have <hi>Received teaches:</hi> Else if <hi>thou or an Angell from heaven, Speak, Preach, Teach.</hi> or <hi>Act</hi> any otherwise, the Church nor any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Member of it, is not to <hi>heare</hi> thee, nor at all to <hi>Submit</hi> unto thee, in thy <hi>Ministeriall-Teaching or Guidance,</hi> but are to <hi>Reject it as that which hath no light in it:</hi> For sayes <hi>Paul</hi> (Gal. 1. 8.) <hi>Let him that speakes otherwise (Angell of Heaven,</hi> or <hi>Angell of the Church,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he be,) <hi>Let him be accursed,</hi> which (as you Interpret in your Booke) is <hi>Excommunicated;</hi> and so undenyably it followes here, If <hi>Archippus</hi> will not be <hi>admonished,</hi> (which is the first Censure <hi>[as it seemes you would not, when you would not hear the Dissatisfaction of those Members that could not concurre with your irregular proceedings in the Church: But would goe on obstinately and Irregularly by the Vote of the Major part (which you had procured to Comply with you) and so refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed your selfe</hi> (in this sence) <hi>to be admonished:]</hi> what followes, but those who are commanded first to <hi>admonish Archippus,</hi> must after, if he will not <hi>Hear the Church</hi> proceed also to the other <hi>Censure;</hi> and <hi>Excommunicate</hi> him: you see <hi>by this</hi> (if the premisses be by and by made Good) that you are already under the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> as you distinguish in your Booke, and if the Major part of the Church be so <hi>Corrupted,</hi> to <hi>Comply with you by an Implicit faith,</hi> that you cannot (in the usuall way) be put under the <hi>practicall part</hi> of it: yet Christ hath so ordained in his <hi>wisdome,</hi> that he affords <hi>a present help</hi> in his word for <hi>this</hi> also; which is that the <hi>Minor part</hi> (in this case) <hi>with-draw from the Major:</hi> According to these Scriptures, (2 <hi>Thess. 3. 6. Rom. 16. 17. 2 Thess. 3. 14. 1 Cor. 5. 11. 1 Tim. 5. 22. Gal. 5. 1. 1 Cor. 7. 23. Gal.</hi> 2. 5.) which being done you are not only <hi>Doctrinally</hi> but <hi>Practically</hi> under this <hi>Censure,</hi> for to be <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,</hi> or (according to Christ) <hi>Rejected,</hi> are one and the same, <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 11.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>those Members</hi> did their <hi>Duty to Declare their Dissatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with your <hi>Irregular Proceedings,</hi> you <hi>reproved them for speaking in the Church,</hi> because <hi>Women must not speake in the Church:</hi> Page 20<seg rend="sup">th</seg>.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35117:4"/> Now a little to <hi>Set you in joynt again</hi> here, Know First, <hi>Women may not speake in the Church, nor usurpe authority,</hi> &amp;c. But notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this; (1) A <hi>Woman</hi> may take you <hi>out of the Church,</hi> and shew you your Errour and set you right <hi>as Priscilla</hi> did <hi>Apolle,</hi> Acts 18. 26. (2) <hi>Women</hi> (fit and able for it) may <hi>pray with</hi> and also <hi>teach others</hi> of their <hi>own Sex,</hi> amongst themselves in their meetings together, as the Apostle commands that they should be <hi>Teachers of good things,</hi> and that <hi>the Elder Women should teach the Younger,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(Titus 3. 3, 4. 5. Jude 20. James</hi> 5 16) yea, you were formerly very free, and also practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it, to have <hi>Women pray in your company,</hi> and your selfe Joyning with them in spirit only, whilest they were <hi>the Mouth</hi> in the <hi>Duty;</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the <hi>Good Women in Cornwall,</hi> which so exceedingly tooke your Heart that you were very much ashamed to think <hi>how short</hi> you came of <hi>them</hi> in the <hi>Gift</hi> or <hi>Spirit of prayer:</hi> and you <hi>Hoped</hi> that this <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise</hi> of their <hi>Praying with the men</hi> would come hereafter to be <hi>more in use.</hi> But this only by the way: (3) I must tell you, They are not commanded to be <hi>altogether silent in the Church it self, and not to speake at all upon no occasion whatsoever,</hi> there is no such <hi>Prohibition</hi> in <hi>all the Scripture: One Text</hi> therefore is to be interpreted by <hi>another:</hi> As when <hi>Mathew</hi> 3. 5. sayes, <hi>All Judea and All the Region round about were Baptised of</hi> John: it must be understood with some <hi>Exception,</hi> which another Scripture <hi>Mentions,</hi> as <hi>Luk.</hi> 7. 30 Namely, Except <hi>the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risees and Lawyers, which Rejected the counsell of God, not being Baptized:</hi> So when some Scriptures say, A <hi>Woman must not speake in the Church,</hi> (namely, <hi>to Teach-Publickly by Prophesying:</hi> as 1 Cor. 14. 34, 35. 1 Tim. 2. 12.) Nor <hi>to usurpe authority over the man</hi> (namely, <hi>to take any publick charge of Pastor or Teacher,</hi> as Diodate on the place) <hi>But to be in silence</hi> (namely in this <hi>Matter or Poynt of Prophesying:) And if they will learn any thing</hi> (namely, <hi>to be further satisfied touching what hath been taught by the Men,</hi> whether <hi>Teaching</hi> by <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Teaching</hi> by <hi>Gift</hi> in the <hi>Church) Let them aske their Husbands at home,</hi> or in case they have none, or none that are <hi>capable to</hi> resolve them, <hi>Let them ask any of the Brethren PRIVATELY</hi> (which is <hi>all one</hi> as to <hi>ask at Home,)</hi> who may after (when it is convenient) <hi>Speake for them in the Church</hi> that they may be <hi>satisfyed,</hi> if they themselves cannot satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them therein: <hi>For</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>it is a shame for women to speake in the Church,</hi> that is, <hi>so to speake as to Teach, or Prophecy, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, or Dispute PƲBLIKELY:</hi> which is <hi>the thing</hi> Expressely spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, in both these fore-mentioned Scriptures; These fore-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Scriptures therefore must be understood, (as the former was) <hi>not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35117:5"/> absolutely and universally,</hi> but with these expresse <hi>Lymmitations,</hi> and with such <hi>Exceptions</hi> as other Scriptures also make <hi>Mention</hi> of, which doe <hi>Require Women in severall other cases to speake in the Church;</hi> Will you <hi>Hear</hi> therefore <hi>Brother,</hi> and will you <hi>learn</hi> in <hi>what cases</hi> they <hi>may</hi> and <hi>ought</hi> to <hi>Speak,</hi> and wherein they should <hi>Sinne,</hi> if they <hi>speake not?</hi> Surely Brother when they performe an <hi>absolute Duty,</hi> and when they <hi>use</hi> no other then the <hi>Liberty</hi> which the Blood of Christ hath <hi>purchased for them, as Believers,</hi> then they doe not <hi>usurpe</hi> nor take to themselves any more <hi>power</hi> or <hi>authority</hi> then is <hi>freely given them</hi> of God and Christ. Now thus it is; First, <hi>When they sing in the Church, as well as the Brethren: Here they speake in the Church;</hi> yea, Here, <hi>they teach and admonish one another in the Church,</hi> (Coloss. 3. 16.) (Secondly.) When they are <hi>asked any Questions concerning others,</hi> To give their <hi>Testimony</hi> concerning them, either concerning persons to be <hi>Admitted,</hi> or touching persons to be <hi>Cenfured,</hi> here also <hi>They must speake in the Church:</hi> (as Acts 12. 14, 15, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 16.) (3dly.) So also concerning <hi>THEMSELVES, at the time of their own ADMISSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON;</hi> when they <hi>professe their Faith before the Lord and the Church,</hi> when they hold forth the work of God upon their own spirits and Gods Gracious dealings with them in his calling of them to <hi>Fellowship</hi> first with <hi>Himselfe,</hi> and now with his <hi>People;</hi> Here it likewise <hi>a speaking in the Church, by the Women as well as the Men,</hi> and that to very good Purpose, for it is found (by experience) to be very <hi>Teaching</hi> and <hi>Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying unto the whole body,</hi> (Though it be not that <hi>Publique Teaching aforesaid,</hi> yet) whilest they are thus <hi>Rendring a reason of the Hope that is in them with meeknesse and Fear,</hi> according to the <hi>Proportion, Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,</hi> and <hi>efficacy</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> which they have <hi>Received,</hi> they doe <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one Contribute and supply something towards the mutuall edifying of the whole a love:</hi> (Mat. 16. 16. 18. 1 Pet. 3. 15 Ephes. 4. 16) (4thly) <hi>They speake in the</hi> Church (by themselves or by a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,) <hi>when upon any occasion Ordinary or Extraordinary,</hi> they are <hi>Sent as Messengers,</hi> or <hi>are recommended unto other Churches,</hi> as <hi>Phebe,</hi> and <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and <hi>Joanna,</hi> and <hi>Mary the Mother of</hi> James, and <hi>other Women,</hi> (Rom. 16. 1. 2. Luke 24. 9, 10, 11. John 20. 17, 18. Mat. 28. 10. Mark 16. 9, 10) (5thly) They speake in the Church, <hi>Where they have an Extraordinary Gift of Prayer and Prophecy:</hi> (I say) <hi>an Extraordinary Gift,</hi> (as 1. <hi>Cor. 11. 5) Every Woman that Prayeth or Prophecieth, &amp;c.</hi> (see the last Annotations on the place,) Thus did <hi>Anna,</hi> Luke 2. 37, 38. <hi>and the four Daughters of Philip:</hi> Acts 21. 9. Hence persons Experienced, learned and Godly, have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that as this was <hi>Extraordinary,</hi> so where there are <hi>Impulses
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35117:5"/> Extraordinary from the Spirit of God, in cases Extraordinary fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out in a Church,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">As in the next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing case here instanced in, or any other such like, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary.</note> There may be the same ground for their speaking now, <hi>(in such cases)</hi> as there was then: though their speaking by way of <hi>Ordinary Prophesying</hi> is forbidden: (6thly) <hi>They speake in the Church: To cleere themselves</hi> from any <hi>Rash, Sudden, undeserved, unadvised, uncharitable</hi> and <hi>unjust Censure, Admonition</hi> or <hi>Reproofe</hi> Irregularly given them by the <hi>Church-Officer: which they ought not to lye down under and submit unto, when they are not guilty of the Foule Faults or Crimes laid to their Charge:</hi> Thus (you know) <hi>Gracious Hannah</hi> did not <hi>Submitt</hi> or <hi>Subject</hi> to that <hi>Rash, Harsh</hi> and <hi>unjust Censure.</hi> But <hi>spake again to Eli</hi> that <hi>Reproved Her:</hi> When he <hi>Counted</hi> and <hi>Called her</hi> (in that <hi>uncomely,</hi> and <hi>unworthy manner,) Drunken Woman, Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Belial,</hi> &amp;c: even for doing or discharging her <hi>Dutie</hi> at that time <hi>in the House of God</hi> (as it seemes upon the like Ground of discharging <hi>a duty in the Church,</hi> (though of <hi>another Kinde,)</hi> you so <hi>unworthily Censured the Gracious S.</hi> which you mention in your Booke: and have <hi>accounted</hi> and <hi>called</hi> her <hi>as bad</hi> or <hi>worse:</hi> and yet will you blame her for her <hi>speaking in the Church?)</hi> See, Read, Consider, lay up, and Remember this Scripture, and let it be your <hi>looking-glasse</hi> for the future; (it is 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 14, 15, 16, 17.) <hi>For these things</hi> (Brother) <hi>were written for our learning, upon whom the ends of the World are come:</hi> (1. Cor. 10. 11.) (Seventhly) <hi>They speake again in the Church likewise (though Privately,) When they Communicate to any Officer or Brother, [that</hi> (if it be needfull) <hi>it may be by him told to the Church,</hi> in Order to their <hi>Reliefe,</hi> or the <hi>Cleering of the truth,] their Dissa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction touching any thing that hath been spoken: Which the Rest of the Church are to Judge of:</hi> (Namely, <hi>Every Individuall Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> in the Church by <hi>a Judgment of discretion,</hi> and <hi>the whole toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> by <hi>a Judgment of Censure:</hi> 1 Cor. 14 29) <hi>or touching any thing which is carrying on, any of the Affairs, Proceedings, or Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sactions in the Church: which ought to be done by the Common and Joynt consent of the whole Church, According to the power given them by Christ, and the Practice of the New-Testament Churches,</hi> (Acts 1. 26. 1 Cor. 5. 4, 5. with 14. 23. Matt. 16. 16. 18, 19. &amp; 18. 17. Phil. 2. 2, 3. Zephany 3. 9. Acts 2. 46. &amp; 4. 32. 1 Cor. 1. 10.) Where you see the <hi>Churches,</hi> in <hi>Jerusalem, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35117:6"/> Philippi, Galatia,</hi> &amp;c: as they were <hi>all of the same constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> so they were <hi>all to practice the same things:</hi> To serve the Lord <hi>with one consent, with one shoulder,</hi> to be <hi>all of one accord, of one heart, of one soul, of one lip, of one language, and all to speake the same thing,</hi> in <hi>all their Administrations, Proceedings</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sactions when they were gathered together:</hi> And <hi>None in particular might Over rule</hi> or <hi>Lord it,</hi> or <hi>carry things Arbitrarily,</hi> or <hi>Assume that Power and Priviledge wholly to themselves,</hi> which by the last will and Testament of Christ, sealed with his Blood, was by him given <hi>in common unto all that had like pretious Faith, unto all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in Church-Estate,</hi> even to the whole Multitude of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>both men and Women, officers and Brithren;</hi> the <hi>whole number of Names,</hi> or <hi>all the Members of the Church Assembled and mett together;</hi> Every thing still (you finde) was to be done <hi>by the Common and Joynt consent, Accord, Agreement, Concurrence</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction of the whole Church that were met together in one place:</hi> Now Brother, <hi>If things must be done by <hi>the whole,</hi> then not by <hi>the Major part;</hi> And if by <hi>the whole,</hi> then of necessity the <hi>Dissa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied</hi> must <hi>speake</hi> their <hi>Dissatisfaction,</hi> in order to the <hi>Satisfying</hi> of their <hi>Doubts</hi> and <hi>Scruples,</hi> or the <hi>Cleering of the Truth:</hi> that they may come to <hi>a Generall and universall concurrence satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, agreement, and consent at length:</hi> And if this cannot be, at last; yet however, <hi>no proceedings</hi> (according to Rule) <hi>can be made in the Church, till all meanes have been first used for this:</hi> Or <hi>till there be in the Dissatisfyed,</hi> (if not <hi>a concurrence,</hi> yet at least) <hi>a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission and yeelding,</hi> (manifested and Declared,) that <hi>the Church</hi> may <hi>proceed: Though often times it so falleth out that the whole Church may see cause to come over to one particular Member that was Dissatisfyed:</hi> as it was in the case of <hi>Paphnutius in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell:</hi> And if the <hi>Minor part of the Church</hi> be in the <hi>Truth,</hi> and cannot yeeld to it that the <hi>Major part</hi> should <hi>Proceed,</hi> and yet whether they <hi>yeeld</hi> or not, whether they are <hi>satisfyed</hi> or not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they <hi>consent</hi> or not, they <hi>will proceed;</hi> and <hi>take the Liberty</hi> or rather <hi>Boldnesse</hi> to <hi>Lord it over them</hi> (as Peter Termes it) or as the word there is, to <hi>over Rule them:</hi> or to <hi>exercise Dominion over their Faith,</hi> or to <hi>Force</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">as <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 42, 43, 44. 1 <hi>Pet. 5. 3. 2 Cor. 1. 24. Ezek. 34. 4. John Ep. 3. v.</hi> 9, 10.</note>
                  <hi>them,</hi> in this case (rather then be <hi>pertakers of their sins) the MINOR PART OƲGHT (according to Rule) To WITHDRAW THEMSELVES</hi> (either for a Time, if the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35117:6"/>
                  <hi>Advice</hi> of <hi>other Churches</hi> may after be a means to <hi>Reconcile</hi> them, or if not, for altogether) <hi>When the Liberties of Christs House and the Lawes of his Kingdome are so wilfully and violently infringed and Broken,</hi> and so the <hi>Matter</hi> appeareth <hi>such,</hi> as upon which, this very <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>with drawing,</hi> in Scripture is <hi>Absolutely</hi> and <hi>Expressely Required:</hi> And hereupon (Brother) I must tell you, They are no <hi>Perjured Persons,</hi> no <hi>Covenant Breakers,</hi> no <hi>Negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of Church Fellowship,</hi> no <hi>Schismatiques,</hi> nor such neither as <hi>seperate from the Church</hi> (or rather as you should have exprest it, <hi>from you and your greater number of men</hi> that so arrogantly <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surpe</hi> and <hi>take to your selves</hi> the <hi>Power, Name,</hi> and <hi>Stile</hi> of the <hi>Church:) to avoyd the Censure:</hi> But on the contrary (Brother) they are such as hearken to the <hi>voyce and call of God and Christ in Scripture,</hi> as well <hi>now</hi> in their <hi>Going out,</hi> as <hi>before in their coming in</hi> to you: yea such as herein are <hi>followers of God as dear children,</hi> and as <hi>obedient children,</hi> doing <hi>the will of God,</hi> and <hi>the will of Christ from the heart, in this their very seperation and withdrawing,</hi> even as they did before in their <hi>withdrawing from the Degenerate and corrupted Parish Churches:</hi> And the true church state of Right Resideth also in such a Part,</hi> (though the <hi>Minor Part) so with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing, according to God;</hi> If they are but <hi>so many</hi> as may reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably have the <hi>Denomination of a Church.</hi> which is not the Case of a Single person nor of two or three. [who in such cases are to <hi>Joynt themselves unto,</hi> or to <hi>walke with any other of the Churches of Christ,</hi> that doe <hi>Keepe close to the Rule,</hi> with whom they may most <hi>comfortably and Satisfactorily close;] the Church having Denomination from.</hi> not its <hi>Major Part</hi> but its <hi>Better part</hi> even from <hi>the few Names left in</hi> Sardis, <hi>who have not defiled their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who are worthy,</hi> (Rev. 3. 4.) Who are <hi>therefore to Purge themselves from the Major Part, (when corrupted) as from Old leaven, that they may be a new lumpe, even as they are unlament'd,</hi> (1 Cor. 5. 7.) (Though a angle person may be in the <hi>Truth,</hi> as <hi>Paphoutius</hi> before mentioned was, and so two or three single persons in like manner, when <hi>all the rest of the Church</hi> may be in <hi>an Errour)</hi> This also <hi>Mr. Burroughs</hi> showes clearly (in his <hi>Heart-Divisions)</hi> Instancing <hi>in such</hi> as liyed in <hi>Darke Times</hi> to <hi>ours;</hi> yet were very <hi>cleare</hi> in <hi>this Poynt;</hi> Namely, That if the <hi>cause</hi> of leaving <hi>Communion with a particular Church</hi> be <hi>Just,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:35117:7"/> proceeding from <hi>love to God, his Saints, a mans own foule,</hi> yea <hi>that very Church</hi> from whence he <hi>departs,</hi> (as sometimes it may,) <hi>Witnessing in a Gracious way against the evill in it,</hi> (such a one,) <hi>He is farre from the Guilt of Schisme:</hi> (2) If the cause of leaving Communion be Just; Then (saith he) <hi>Those who give this cause are the Schismaticks,</hi> not <hi>those who with-draw upon it.</hi> Thus <hi>the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the Church may be the Schismaticks,</hi> and <hi>a Private Member with-drawing may be free: Suarez</hi> a great Jesuite, in his disputation <hi>(De Schismat,)</hi> sayes in some cases <hi>the Pope</hi> may be <hi>a Schismatick.</hi> If <hi>Governours</hi> shall enjoyne any thing upon the <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>any Member,</hi> that is <hi>Sinne:</hi> or if they shall <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle evill</hi> in the <hi>Publick worship,</hi> so that there can be no <hi>Joyning with their worship,</hi> but there must be likewise <hi>a Joyning with sinne,</hi> in this case if any <hi>with-draw from them they are the Schismaticks, not those who with-draw;</hi> they are <hi>Fugati,</hi> not <hi>Fugitivi. The Blame of Schisme sayes learned</hi> Voetius <hi>must not be upon those who forsake such as have forsaken</hi> Christ <hi>and the Ancient Faith; but upon those who have thus forsaken Christ and his Truth:</hi> When the <hi>Second Counsell of</hi> Nice set up <hi>Image worship,</hi> many thousands could not yeeld to it but were forced to <hi>with-draw,</hi> who was the <hi>Schismaticall party there,</hi> but <hi>the Synod</hi> and <hi>those who Joyned with it?</hi> Yea further, (saith <hi>Mr. Burroughs)</hi> If they <hi>Impose</hi> that which is <hi>not necessary</hi> (though in it selfe <hi>not sinfull)</hi> and <hi>will not Bear with the weaknesses of such as thinke it to be evill;</hi> if upon that they be forced to <hi>withdraw;</hi> in this, <hi>the Governours are the Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks also;</hi> the <hi>cause</hi> of the <hi>Rent</hi> is in them; They ought in such things to <hi>Bear the weaknesses of their Brethren,</hi> and not <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously to require of them</hi> those things that there is <hi>no necessity of;</hi> If such things be sinne to their Brethrens Consciences, if they will stand upon it, to injoyne them, they lay a necessity upon them to with-draw from them. God will not lay the Indictment of <hi>Schism,</hi> thus, <hi>Such a one Departed from the Communion of such a Church because he would not doe what was lawfull to be done;</hi> but thus, <hi>you Imposed that upon your Brother which there was no necessity of, and would not forbear him, but caused him by your imperiousnesse and stiffenesse, to depart from Communion with you: It is true,</hi> (sayes God,) <hi>the thing might have been done, but it was not necessary, it was out of Conscience to me that they forbore, the weaknesse is theirs,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35117:7"/> but the Schisme is yours:</hi> Soe <hi>Mr. Burroughs; Heart-Divisions.</hi> Page 173, 174. Hereby (I hope) you see cleerly, that they who <hi>Cause</hi> the <hi>Schisme</hi> or <hi>Division,</hi> they are the <hi>Dividers,</hi> and the <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> and not those who <hi>with-draw</hi> from them according to divine appointment, and an expresse command given them on that behalfe; in 2 Thess. 3. 6. and in the other Scriptures before quoted. <hi>(P.</hi> 4.)</p>
            <p>Consider therefore (Brother) <hi>what you have done,</hi> (in this late <hi>Excommunication?)</hi> Also <hi>wherefore you have done it?</hi> and likewise <hi>how you have done it?</hi> and be perswaded now <hi>to Repent of it;</hi> if the Lord hath yet given you to see <hi>Cause</hi> for it, in respect of both <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Manner:</hi> [for <hi>by Repenting,</hi> you will <hi>Cleere your selfe more</hi> then <hi>by many Books Publishing:</hi> as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11.] And if not, be pleased to consider with me yet a little further some of the fore mentioned Scriptures; and tell me (Brother) <hi>When Matthias was added in thi Roome of Judas by Common-Consent,</hi> Acts 1. 26. <hi>The Number of Names then met together being about an hundred and twenty, vers.</hi> 15th <hi>were not these one hundred and twenty persons (thinke you) Men and Women? Apostles and Brethren, and all likewise giving their common consent for his Admission? He was added or numbred with the Eleven Apostles</hi> (say the last Annotations) <hi>by Common-Declaration of their Generall</hi> or <hi>universall Consent,</hi> Reade also <hi>Cottons way of the Churches, what Common-consent meanes, if you understand it not?</hi> If you would interpret it to be meant <hi>here</hi> as in <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>worldly Corporations</hi> and <hi>Courts,</hi> where the <hi>Major part (according to their Lawes) Exercise the Authority;</hi> and take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them <hi>to ever Rule the Minor, Christ tells you EXPRESLY that it shall not be so amongst you:</hi> (Mark. 10. 42, 43, 44. 1 Pet. 5. 3. 2 Cor. 1. 24.) So that herein you are much out, and <note place="margin">* and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise <hi>expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemns it.</hi> Ezek. 34. 4. &amp; John Ep. 3. <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10.</note> doe <hi>Differ</hi> in your Judgment <hi>from the Truth,</hi> even <hi>as much as the Church Differs from the World,</hi> Or as much as <hi>the Rule and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion which the Heathen Exercise in the World Differs from that Rule and Government, which Christ hath appointed in his Church.</hi> Again (in 1 Cor. 5.) <hi>When the indestrious person was to be cast out by the whole Church gathered together: Did the Apostle meane only the Officers and Major part of the Brethren of that Church? and that the Rest, together with the Women, might stay at home, and needed not come together to inflict this Censure? If they had but a Major part to doe it, was this enough? doth he say so Brother?</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35117:8"/> Again (in 16th <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 18, 19. <hi>Doth Christ speake to Peter</hi> (according to learned <hi>Hooker</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> in answer of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therford,</hi> on the Place) <hi>Not as an Apostle, not as an Elder, not as an officer,</hi> but <hi>as a Beleever, To thee will I give the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven, and whatsoever thou shalt binde on earth shall he bound in Heaven?</hi> Doth he (I say) speake unto him <hi>as a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever? as one making that profession of his faith before the Lord and his Brethren (which flesh and Blood had not Revealed to him but the Father only,) And doth the Lord tell us that upon that Rock, even Christ himselfe so beleeved on, and that faith in Him,</hi> (I say that Faith so far forth as men can judge of it) <hi>so Openly or Ʋisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Professed He would build his visible Church, and give every such visible Believer these Keyes?</hi> Then I beseech you how came you to take away these <hi>Keyes from the Minor part of the Brethren, and from the Sisters?</hi> Are they not all <hi>Believers?</hi> Have <hi>Women</hi> no <hi>Soules?</hi> or no <hi>Faith?</hi> nor <hi>many of the Brethren neither, that that which is given Joyntly unto them all, as Believers; must be not usurped wholly by some though the Major part, and detained from the rest?</hi> Methinks you should Blush to Publish such things as these to the World.</p>
            <p>Again, when you would tye the rest of the Members from falling off from you by the renewing of their Covenant. <hi>Page</hi> 39. Are you not ashamed to make them <hi>Swear</hi> (as you Interpret their <hi>Church Covenant</hi> to be no other then <hi>an Oath) that they will submit to your teaching, and Ministeriall guidance, without any Lymmitation, Restriction, or pr<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> whatsoever mentioned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with?</hi> is it not enough, if they submit unto you according to God? or to your teaching when it is <hi>according to that of the annoynting which teaches them all things, which is truth, and is no Lye?</hi> and when in your <hi>speaking</hi> you <hi>speake as the Oracles of God?</hi> But must they <hi>submit unto it,</hi> (right or wrong) <hi>whatever it be?</hi> There are many <hi>False Teachers</hi> gone forth, and many <hi>strange Doctrines</hi> also taught, and especially <hi>in these our Dayes,</hi> and must they not now <hi>try the Spirits?</hi> must they not <hi>prove all things?</hi> must they not <hi>search the Scriptures,</hi> must they not <hi>see if <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or no?</hi> if it be the <hi>voyce of Christ or no?</hi> if <hi>as Oracle of God or no? Christ</hi> bid them doe so, <hi>the Apostle</hi> bid them doe so: <hi>And if you or an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell from heaven Preach any other Doctrine then they have taught:</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:35117:8"/> Ought they not to <hi>Reject it,</hi> and <hi>not to submit unto it?</hi> Are there not many <hi>Blinde leaders of the Blinde?</hi> and doth not the Lord also complain, that <hi>the Teachers of his people cause them to erre?</hi> yea, have not the <hi>Best of Teachers,</hi> and those <hi>most sound in the faith,</hi> their <hi>Mixtures?</hi> Will any pretend to be <hi>Infallible in all things?</hi> Must they not then (if there be cause) <hi>Admonish Archippus,</hi> and not goe along with him in all things which he <hi>Teaches</hi> or <hi>doth</hi> by <hi>an Implicit faith?</hi> much lesse enter into <hi>a Covenant</hi> and into <hi>an Oath</hi> to doe so? <hi>Paul</hi> himself requires no more but this, that we <hi>Follow him, as he followes Christ,</hi> (1 Cor. 11. 1.) The truth is, we are to <hi>Follow the Lamb wheresoever he goes,</hi> But if we resolve to <hi>follow also our Ministeriall Guides and Leaders wheresoever they go,</hi> Christ tells us <hi>we may possibly follow them so long till we both fall into the Ditch:</hi> Indeed after this, when you make them Covenant to submit to the oversight of the <hi>Ruling Elders, Ruling according to Gods Word:</hi> you say something But when you make them <hi>Swear</hi> to submit unto you, <hi>(the Teaching Elder,)</hi> why did you not add likewise <hi>Teaching according to Gods Word?</hi> Perhaps you might sometimes (though you knew it not) teach some things which might be, not according to Gods word, Then <hi>your speaking those things</hi> was not <hi>Christs voyce</hi> but <hi>your own voyce,</hi> or <hi>the voyce of a stranger:</hi> And Christ sayes of his Sheep, (and approves of it) That <hi>a stranger they will not hear, nor a stranger they will not follow,</hi> (John 10.) Now peradventure as you were <hi>a stranger in this place,</hi> so sometimes also you might seeme to them, to be <hi>as a stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger even in this sence,</hi> And <hi>this</hi> possibly might be <hi>one Ground</hi> of <hi>those Members with-drawing from you, to hear others:</hi> (2) you might possibly from the very first, be apprehended to be of <hi>but weak or mean abilities to edifie them,</hi> (as God hath not dispenced either <hi>Gifts</hi> or <hi>Grace</hi> to all alike) and yet might be by the <hi>Major part of your men</hi> admitted: Now here likewise the Rule is expresse (in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 20.) <hi>Let all things</hi> (as namely <hi>Singing, Praying, Proph<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sying, Interpretting, Teaching,</hi> and so likewise <hi>the Duty of Hearing,) be done unto edifying;</hi> They must therefore (to this end,) <hi>Take heed how,</hi> and <hi>what,</hi> and <hi>whom they hear,</hi> that so <hi>this Duty may be done to their edifying:</hi> But you will say to leave our meeting may be against the <hi>Peace of the Church:</hi> Answ. The Rule is as expresse here also, <hi>(Rom.</hi> 14. 19.) <hi>They must follow
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35117:9"/> the things which make for Peace and whereby one may edifie another.</hi> But if <hi>One cannot edifie the other,</hi> what then? <hi>shall they come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not for the Better, but for the worse?</hi> No; <hi>Peace</hi> is <hi>good,</hi> but <hi>Truth</hi> is <hi>Better, Peace</hi> is <hi>Good,</hi> but <hi>Holinesse</hi> is <hi>better; Peace</hi> is <hi>Good</hi> but <hi>Edifying</hi> is <hi>Better:</hi> wherefore (saith the Apostle) <hi>Let all things be done unto Edifying;</hi> Saints must <hi>Discerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt things that differ,</hi> and (where both cannot be had) are to pursue and follow after <hi>those things which are most excellent,</hi> (as <hi>Philip</hi> 1. 10) A particular Church therefore, <hi>(in this case,</hi> and upon <hi>these Grounds,</hi> never was, nor is, nor ought to be a Prison (much lesse a perpetuall one, whereby they should be <hi>all their life time subject to Bondage,)</hi> to the Saints: But Saints <hi>here,</hi> ought to be <hi>such</hi> as the Apostle exhorts them, <hi>Earnest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders for he faith which was once Delivered to them, and to stand fast in all those liberties and Freedomes which Christ hath purchased them: Being bought with a Price they may not be the servants of men, nor the subjects of men, nor be brought under the power of any thing,</hi> as the Apostle speakes of himselfe. So <hi>(Gal: 2. 5:) To whom we gave place by subjection, no not for an hour, that the truth of the Gospell might continue with you.</hi> Namely, the <hi>whole truth,</hi> both that of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and that of <hi>Discipline:</hi> both must continue with the Saints: Now here (Brother) <hi>Did you not with-hold some part of this Truth at least, in unrighteousnesse;</hi> as to <hi>Abridge the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> (and especially these,) <hi>of their Rights and Priviledges?</hi> Then if they were (3 times, or more) absent from your meetings <hi>was there not a cause?</hi> or if they are with drawn for altogether? Hear what Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> says to this likewise, <hi>Where a man (saith he) cannot have his soule edifyed in some Ordinances and Truths of Great moment, which that Church whereof he now is, shall Deny: And also where he is in great danger of being seduced to evill, he may depart from that Church to another. Heart Divisions,</hi> P. 175.</p>
            <p>Again Brother, (to convince you of your <hi>Errours</hi> yet a little further,) <hi>Why doe you so often contradict your selfe in your Booke?</hi> as Page 3. you say <hi>The Authority of Excommunication Pertaineth to the Whole Church,</hi> and quote Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> for it, on (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.) and in your <hi>Rules for Admission,</hi> and for <hi>walking in Church Order;</hi> you say, <hi>by the Church may be meant the Major number of the men, And that such Matters of Weight and Moment</hi> (as casting out of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35117:9"/> the Church <hi>by the Pastor and Officers,) may be done by the consent of the Greater part of the men:</hi> Surely (Brother) Those who have covenanted to submit unto you, in <hi>this Teaching of yours;</hi> they have Covenanted to give <hi>a very blinde Obedience to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Page 5th you say: 3 <hi>things are requisite to Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication (1) It must be from a good intention of the Heart, and not from a revengefull Principle:]</hi> Now in your <hi>Practice,</hi> your <hi>High, Passionate, Bitter, Angry, Wrathfull, Ridged-termes, Epithetes, and Odious comparisons which you give them, and make of them in your Book, for their with drawing from you; seemes to have some Tincture of this revengefull principle,</hi> (2) you say, <hi>[it should be when the cause is just and cleere, and cleerly proved:]</hi> First, for <hi>the cause,</hi> which you mention, as namely, <hi>Telling a lye three times</hi> or more, and <hi>Disobedience</hi> (but <hi>what lye,</hi> or <hi>what kinde of Disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> you mention not:) I shall leave this, to the Parties concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to speake unto, or let it rest till I know the truth in <hi>matter of Fact,</hi> which your Booke pretended at the first view, to discover but doth not: <hi>Only</hi> telling you for the present these 2 or 3 things. (1) (Whatever you affirm in your Sermon to the <hi>contrary,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 18. (upon <hi>Isa</hi> 63. 8.) He saith <hi>[This is such a spot as is not in Gods own chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren]</hi> yet Reader see that even <hi>this very spot,</hi> is charged upon <hi>this very people</hi> which God <hi>here</hi> speakes of, at the 10. verse: So likewise more expresly, <hi>Ch.</hi> 30. 9. &amp; 57. 4. &amp; <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 20.</note> yet <hi>Those in Scripture who have been most eminently Godly, Have through infirmity so miscarried, as to be overtaken with this fault (of Lying)</hi> as not only <hi>Sarah, Rachel, the Midwives, and other Women</hi> in Scripture, But likewise, <hi>Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, Joseph, the Patriarchs, Jeremy, Elisha, Sampson, David</hi> and <hi>Peter:</hi> And the <hi>three last, each of them 3 times</hi> or more, <hi>(even as often as you affirme of this Woman (yet neither of them all were ever so Cursed, Reviled, Counted, called, Ranked or Handled by God or man as you have done this Woman</hi> (2) Whereas you would argue her to be <hi>an Hypocrite or Childe of H<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll,</hi> from this: Because God sayes of his People, <hi>They are my people, Children that will not lye:</hi>—And <hi>without are Dogs,—and whosoever loveth and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a lye:</hi> I must a little set you right here; and tell you, That <hi>Gods Children,</hi> or <hi>those that are born of God,</hi> Though they sin by lying or otherwise, yet <hi>(so farre forth as they are renewed) they doe not love it.</hi> But can say with <hi>Paul, what I hate that I doe, and what I Doe I allow not, I approve not, I love not, and so cannot be Ranked with such as doe love and make a lye:</hi> yea, I must tell you further, <hi>Soe farre forth as they are renewed, They will not lye, they cannot lye;</hi> (and so that other Scriptures ought to be understood
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35117:10"/> if you will take the words in the <hi>Strictest sense)</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Though here, <hi>(Isa.</hi> 63. 8.) It is cleerly meant of their Keeping <hi>Promise</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> with God, that God did expect <hi>this,</hi> as a fruit of his mercy to them: or (to speake after the manner of men) He did <hi>Assure</hi> or <hi>promise</hi> himselfe thus much from them (when he was to bring <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem out of <hi>Aegypt)</hi> That they would now cleave unto him (according to their Covenant also) and <hi>would Keepe his Law,</hi> Namely, <hi>Not to returne to Aegypt,</hi> (which was one B<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nch of it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 16) Seing he was to <hi>be their Saviour:</hi> and was now to Redeeme them from that place of Bondage; But yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this, (after they were delivered) They answered not Gods expectation herein, but dealt unfaithfully in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (verse. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.) and <hi>walked to goe down to</hi> Aegypt, <hi>(Isa.</hi> 30 2.) and hereupon are called: <hi>Lying Children, A seed of Falshood, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in whom is no Faith</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>in this poynt, of me keeping his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises with God,</hi> let him who hath cast out the <hi>Pretended Lyer</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider how often his own consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath convinced him of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>such a Lyer</hi> himselfe.</note>
               <hi>They cannot sinne that sin nor any other sin with their WHOLE WILL, with the Regenerate Part;</hi> But as the Apostle speaks, <hi>With their mind they serve the Law of God though with their flesh the Law of sin,</hi> If then they doe that which they would not, they consent unto the Law that it is good: Now then it is noe more they that do it, but sin that dwelleth in them, So the <hi>Apostle</hi> (Rom. 7.) Speaking of <hi>himselfe;</hi> This therefore is the State <hi>(Brother)</hi> not of the <hi>Children of Hell that are of their father the Devill,</hi> (as you have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) But of the <hi>Children of God,</hi> of <hi>such as have a father in Heaven;</hi> (3) I must tell you, <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry untruth is not a ly:</hi> if it were, <hi>this Odium would Retort upon your selfe,</hi> with very much <hi>shame,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at <hi>this Time,</hi> for what you have <hi>now</hi> (by this your Officious Servant) <hi>written.</hi> But if here after also, <hi>[besides from what is written here, where</hi> (as Christ spake to that <hi>Evill Servant) I doe but Judge of your proceedings and Actings even by what I have OƲT OF YOƲR OWN MOƲTH]</hi> the <hi>Cause</hi> Appear not to be <hi>Just</hi> and <hi>Cleere,</hi> (when the yet <hi>Hidden things of darknesse shall be brought to light,</hi> by the <hi>other Parties,</hi> who have not yet been <hi>Heard to speak)</hi> Then surely whilest you pretended to be so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly <hi>Proceeding in an Ordinance of Christ,</hi> it will be found (with yet more full Evidence) that you were but <hi>Transgressing an Ordinance of Christ,</hi> and that <hi>it was iniquity, even your so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne meeting,</hi> (as <hi>Isa.</hi> 1 13.) And so <hi>your curse causelesse, (as The Devill take her, and Take her Divell, Torment her and vex her;)</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hic</hi> Vox Populi, Vox Dei <hi>esse non astimabitur; Haud Plus quam</hi> Vox LODOVICI STUCLAEI (&amp; Majoris sui numeri Hominum,) Vox Ecclesiae <hi>esse astimabitur.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>will not come,</hi> Prov. 26. 2 Nor what you <hi>This day</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">March 8. 1657.</note>
               <hi>Bound on Earth</hi> be <hi>Bound in Heaven</hi> (as you peremptorily conclude, P. 14.) nor the Pretended <hi>offenders</hi> be <hi>feared, Scared,</hi> or <hi>Troubled,</hi> (as you in your late Sermon Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined) nor think themselves the lesse worthy of <hi>a name in the House of God,</hi> for your so tradu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cing them, (P. 9.) nor ever the <hi>fitter for Fellowship with Damned Spirits,</hi> because you so judge them (P. 11.) not ever
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35117:10"/>
               <hi>the further off from Fellowship with the Lord and his people,</hi> for <hi>yours</hi> and your <hi>Major part</hi> of the <hi>Brethrens</hi> casting them out of <hi>your Fellowship;</hi> But they will find that Good-Word, eminently ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled to them <hi>(Isa. 66. 5.) your Brethren that hated you, and that cast you out for my Names Sake, said let the Lord be glorified, but he shall appear to your Joy, and they shall be ashamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the meane time Brother, be pleased to Consider, that if <hi>the Whole Church</hi> did not indeed before hand <hi>determine</hi> this <hi>Matter,</hi> (and that likewise from Apparrent and Clear Rules or Examples in Scripture) Namely that <hi>this Censure was due unto these persons</hi> (whom you have thus cast out,) <hi>you have</hi> then Certainly sinned Egregiously, even in the very <hi>Matter</hi> of it: and if they did not as <hi>unanimously</hi> (according to Rule) <hi>concurre with you</hi> in the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> of it, you did as much offend in the <hi>Manner</hi> of it: Besides your ill Management in other particulars, and Respects, relating also to the <hi>Manner</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>But (2) As the <hi>Cause must be Just and Clear,</hi> So you adde, <hi>that it must be clearly proved;</hi> But it seemes, <hi>All things were not Clearely proved,</hi> for some things you doe affirme, with this Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zo, <hi>(If your Memory faile not,</hi> P. 21.) and others with this, <hi>(as you were informed,</hi> P. 23.) and <hi>as it is reported,</hi> P. 10.)</p>
            <p>(3) You say, <hi>[This Sentence must be Executed according to Christs Order, that is, after Private Adminition:]</hi> But that these persons <hi>Refused Admonition,</hi> and <hi>Contemned Admonition,</hi> though they had it <hi>by a brother, or two, Severall-times,</hi> yea, <hi>both privately, and publickly:</hi> But here you breake <hi>Christs-Order,</hi> if you labour not first of all, <hi>to prepare them for it,</hi> as namely <hi>to Convince them, and to shew them their sin,</hi> before you proceed to the formalities of <hi>Admonishing,</hi> and <hi>Reproving</hi> them; (according to Levit. 19. &amp; Mat. 18.) <hi>For if you take upon you to admonish them, of that which they see not themselves to be guilty of, no marvel then, if they hearken not to your Admonition:</hi> It may be, <hi>you Admonished them for doing their duty, in Declaring, their Dissatisfaction at some of your Proceedings,</hi> Or <hi>for speaking in the Church only to desire Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction,</hi> then you deserved Admonition your self, for so doing: You say also, (Page 20.) <hi>That they would discover their Dislike of persons Propounded after the Church had concluded to Receive them:</hi> But did you doe <hi>your Dutie, to ask them before hand, if they were all of One Accord, and of One mind touching the Reception of those Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons?</hi> Or <hi>if the Brethren &amp; Sisters were all satisfied touching it? And if not, Did you tell them that they had their Libertie,</hi> and it was now seasonable for them <hi>to speake</hi> either <hi>themselves,</hi> Or, (if that offend you) <hi>by a Brother</hi> (if it were one of the Sisters,) <hi>before you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35117:11"/> Proceeded?</hi> If you failed in this, you were your selfe <hi>Deepest,</hi> yea, (which is more) you were also <hi>First,</hi> if not <hi>Alone</hi> in the <hi>Transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> and therefore If you had had your due, should your self have had an <hi>Admonition:</hi> Againe—<hi>After the Church had concluded, or (as you say) Given Decission:</hi> But Brother <hi>what Church</hi> doe you meane? Doe you meane <hi>your selfe, and the Major-Part of the Men?</hi> if So, there being <hi>no such Church</hi> of Divine Appointment, in the Scriptures of the New-Testament, this your <hi>Church-Decissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was <hi>a meere nullity</hi> by the Lawes of Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> (Page 20.) you say, <hi>One of them Never Reproved Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately: and so was not faithfull to the rule of Christ?</hi> Perhaps the offences were <hi>Publick</hi> and such as <hi>So offend,</hi> are to be <hi>So reproved:</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 20. <hi>If therefore you transgresse in the Church, before all, you must not think to be told of it in your Closet:</hi> Deare <hi>Brother,</hi> So <hi>(upon the Hopes I have of Gaining you to the truth)</hi> I still <hi>Call you,</hi> and <hi>Account you,</hi> and <hi>not as an Enemy,</hi> though I <hi>thus admonish you:</hi> But because I doe not <hi>Hate,</hi> but <hi>Love you in my heart,</hi> therefore <hi>I would not suffer sin upon you,</hi> Pardon me if I have not done it with <hi>so much meeknesse and gentlenesse and tendernesse towards you,</hi> as I have aimed at and desired: if there be some little or small <hi>mixture</hi> (Here and there) <hi>of Quicknesse, or Sharpenesse,</hi> yet consider it may make you <hi>the more sound in the Faith,</hi> (as Titus 1. 13.) <hi>The Lord also will pardon the iniquity of our holy-things,</hi> So should <hi>we pardon, and forgive each other:</hi> yet, However, let not this <hi>Defect</hi> or <hi>want in me,</hi> any way hinder it, But Earnestly beg of God that you may be <hi>Recovered,</hi> and that <hi>this which hath been said, May be as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Balme which may not break your head; Oh that it might be a kindnesse to you;</hi> Then Indeed I should think the time well spent, that was taken to write to you: Consider, then what I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and the Lord give you understanding in all things. So prayeth <hi>Your Brother and Companion in the Kingdome and patience of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ,</hi> [Whose hearts desire and Prayer to God for you, is that you may be Saved, Healed, Renned, and Recovered from the Corruption of your heart, and the error of your way: And that you may walk for the future more Humbly with the Lord, and with his People; even in a Brotherly Equallity, in the Church of Christ: with Patience and Forbearance &amp; long-suffering towards All: as shewing, <hi>All Meeknesse towards All Men, and in Lowlinesse of Mind, Esteeming every one,</hi> (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Church or out of it) <hi>better then your selfe:</hi> (as Tit. 3. 2. &amp; Phil. 2. 3. with 1 Tim. 1. 15.]</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. T.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>